<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true testimonie of a faithfull subiect containing seuerall exhortations to all estates, to continue them in their due obedience: together with the reward of a faithfull subiect to his prince. Also a thanksgiuing to God for the happie deliuery of the house of Parliament from the late horrible treason.</title>
            <title>Right way to heaven</title>
            <author>R. V. (Richard Vennard), d. 1615?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111516</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1042:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true testimonie of a faithfull subiect containing seuerall exhortations to all estates, to continue them in their due obedience: together with the reward of a faithfull subiect to his prince. Also a thanksgiuing to God for the happie deliuery of the house of Parliament from the late horrible treason.</title>
                  <title>Right way to heaven</title>
                  <author>R. V. (Richard Vennard), d. 1615?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By R. Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: R.V., i.e. Richard Vennard.</note>
                  <note>A reprinting, with new verse, of most of the prose portion of: The right way to heaven.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Allegiance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <figure>
               <figDesc>ornamental border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>THE TRVE TESTIMONIE OF A FAITHFVLL SVBIECT: Containing ſeuerall exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to all eſtates, to continue them in their due obedience: together with the reward of a faithfull ſubiect to his Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo a thankſgiuing to God for the happie deliuery of the houſe of Parliament from the late horrible treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of James I</figDesc>
                  <head>IACOBVS REX.</head>
                  <l>Bleſſed be they that bleſſe you.</l>
                  <l>And curſed be they that curſe you.</l>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS most excellent Maiestie, my moſt gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt renowned Soueraigne, as before your Maieſties co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this Crowne, I did in your Realme of Scotland make apparant my vnfained loue to your Highneſſe: ſo do I now on bended knees moſt humbly beſeech your royall Maieſtie to accept this little hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of my hearts moſt faithfull affection; wherein my feeling of Gods mercies, my knowledge of your gracious goodneſſe, and my care of my countries well-doing, hath made me take ſuch paines. As if it may be pleaſing in your ſight, ſhall breed no little glory to my ſoule: who kneeling
<pb facs="tcp:11833:3"/>
at your royall feete, do beſeech the God of all glorie to endue your Highneſſe with his infinite bleſſings, and long to preſerue your royall Maieſtie in all ioyfull health, and proſperous life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties most faithfull and loyall ſubiect in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie of all loyaltie, <hi>R. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="front_matter">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:3"/>
            <head>What a faithful ſubiect is, together with his reward.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
               </hi> Good ſubiect next to the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem that adornes a Princes head, is the chiefeſt ornament that decores his dignitie. He is as the precious Baulme that annoints his browes, and is nearer to his heart then his Scepter in his right hand: as ſweete in his noſtrels as the groues of <hi>Gilead,</hi> &amp; more precious in his ſight then <hi>Salomons</hi> Iuory throne couered with pureſt gold.</p>
            <p>His heart is clothed with peace, like mount Oliuet: and his eyes as harmeleſſe as the ſight of a Doue.</p>
            <p>His tongue ſounds like the harp of <hi>Dauid:</hi> and his lips deliuer the happineſſe of loyaltie.</p>
            <p>His eares are the portals that receiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding: and all perfection from thence
<pb facs="tcp:11833:4"/>
is conducted to the heart.</p>
            <p>His hands are ready to fight the battels of the Lord: and his feete (ſhunning the ſteps of bloud) are bent alwayes to walke in the paths of innocencie.</p>
            <p>Thus excellent in the ſight of his Prince ſhines a faithfull ſubiect, more gorgeous then the Ephod of <hi>Aron,</hi> and more ſumptuous then <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his royaltie.</p>
            <p>Whoſo is thus to his Prince and countrey, the Lord wil proſper him, and he ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in an euerlaſting generation.</p>
            <p>And for one of theſe benefits he receiues on earth, he ſhall haue a million in heauen.</p>
            <p>For one of theſe perfections he partakes of in this world, numbers aboue number ſhal at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in the world to come.</p>
            <p>And his Prince ſhall thus pray for him, and bleſſe him as <hi>Salomon</hi> did his ſubiects.</p>
            <p>And the King turned his face, and bleſſed all the congregation of Iſrael, and ſaid, Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, who ſpake with his mouth to <hi>Dauid</hi> my father, &amp; hath with his
<pb facs="tcp:11833:4"/>
hand fulfilled it.</p>
            <p>And though my ſelfe may ſay with <hi>Eſay,</hi> I am as a worme and no man, yet (I ſpeake it in deſpite of vaine-glory) I would with all my heart, as an <hi>Iſack</hi> in the hands of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſerue as a ſacrifice to do my Prince and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey good.</p>
            <p>For ſurely he cannot be the true ſeruant of God, that is not a faithful ſubiect to his Prince. Neither wold I iudge any felicity in this world anſwerable to that, if once my ſoule might be employed to pleaſe my Prince, and benefite my countrey.</p>
            <p>For all the offices of humanitie depend on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon thoſe principall performances.</p>
            <p>For I know by that meanes there comes a bleſsing from a far, a reward full of ioy, which none elſe are worthy to obtaine: which reward I heartily pray the great Rewarder of all to ſend to the true loyall and faithfull ſubiect. And ſo with one voice, proceeding from one vnity of heart, let vs all ſay faithfully, God ſaue the King.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:5"/>
            <head>An Exhortation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue all ſubiects in their due obedience.</head>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <head>To the reuerend Lord Biſhops, and the Cleargie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as your Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical office is giuen you from God, as the next principall members vnder the head, to gouerne the commonwealth of this myſticall bodie: and that there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at your hands an extraordinary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie touching the function of the ſoule, let me intreate you to be as vigilant as the fiue wiſe virgines, hauing oyle alwayes in your lampes, againſt the bridegroome cometh foorth of his chamber. Your office is the ſoule of the laity, the hart of gouernment,
<pb facs="tcp:11833:5"/>
and the very Epitomie of all obedience. From you (as the Moone borroweth her light of the Sunne) all inferiour Miniſters take their order of perfection. Let then your doctrine be pure and ſtedfaſt, like <hi>Moſes</hi> buſh, that alwayes burned, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conſumed. Your preaching in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon: and your conuerſation as ſpotleſſe as the ſacrifice of Turtles. You beſt know what plenty of Manna hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Iſrael, &amp; how many omers full eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ought to gather. Be not any of you the firſt that gather more then is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and in miſtruſt of Gods benefites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole land with the vice of Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice: you ought rather to be like Pellicans in the wilderneſſe, who in tender loue pick the bloud from their breaſts to feede their yong ones.</p>
               <p>You ſee with your viſible eies how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully Almightie God hath now preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Kings Maieſtie, and your ſelues, from the ſnare of your manifold enemies:
<pb facs="tcp:11833:6"/>
and in you principally lieth the ſacrifice of thankſgiuing. It is you that ought to dance before the Tabernacle, and to go with the people to the Ark of Couenant: that your righteouſneſſe may bud like Aarons rod.</p>
               <p>It is you that ought to flie foorth from this toſſed Arke, and like the Doue bring the oliue branch of peace in your mouths, &amp; tel the people, that if they returne, God will be their God, and ſend a truce to their diſtreſſed ſoules by you his Ambaſſadors.</p>
               <p>Flie not to Tarſhiſh when you are ſent to Niniue, leaſt deuouring deſtruction at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you; nor with the man of God, go not out of the way, leaſt a Lion teare you in peeces: but ſtill be conuerſant with the Lord, that your faces may ſhine with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes when he came from the mount, and bring the image of Gods glory to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in your foreheads.</p>
               <p>You muſt beare with Aaron the breaſt-plate of iudgment vpon your harts. There muſt be grauen vpon your forefronts holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:11833:6"/>
to the Lord: and your ſounds muſt be heard when you go into the holy places before him.</p>
               <p>So ſhall ye ſtand like mount Sinai, neuer to be remoued: and your golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes ſhine in the Temples of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Remember the charge your maiſter Chriſt gaue to his ſeruant Peter, binding him three times by his feruent loue and the deare affection he bare to his maiſter, to feed his ſheepe.</p>
               <p>To be with Paul the faithfull Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Ieſus Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you through vs: we pray you in Chriſts ſtead that ye be reconciled vnto God: with Paul likewiſe to be an example of life and doctrine, as in theſe words, And follow hard toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore as many as be perfect be thus minded: if yee be otherwiſe, God ſhall reueale euen the ſame vnto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11833:7"/>
Ye are (moſt Reuerend) the ſalt of the earth; which wanting ſauour, is to be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote.</p>
               <p>Ye are the light of the world. A cittie that is ſet on a hill cannot be hid: let your lights therefore ſo ſhine, that thoſe which ſee your good workes may glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</p>
               <p>Thus, vnworthy to counſell ſo graue aduiſements, as if the body ſhould inſtruct the ſoule, I onely like a traueller in this pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, ſeeing ſome go out of their way, tell them there is a better, a more perfect, and a ſtraighter. So referring you to your maſters reward, who hates a hidden talent, I beſeech that God who guided Iſrael by day in a pillar of cloud, and by night in a pillar of fire, to direct your earthly bodies and ſpirituall ſoules to his ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:7"/>
               <head>To the true Nobilitie of this Realme.</head>
               <p>TO ye (right Honorable) that are the props and ſupporters of a kingdom, that like <hi>Atlas</hi> ſhould beare the waight of heauen on your ſhoulders, giue me leaue to ſtretch forth the arteries of my heart: &amp; as in a tempeſtuous time, in peace vnite you together like one bodie obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to one principall head.</p>
               <p>In that worthy member the heart, the monarke ſeate of our <hi>microcoſmus,</hi> ſhould be your reſidence, within whoſe center (as in a Princes court) are diuers receptacles for you to inhabite in. Then as branches extending from the lofty Cedar, being fed by one roote, do notwithſtanding cheriſh one another with their naturall ſappe. So like the ſtocke of Nobilitie, deſcended
<pb facs="tcp:11833:8"/>
from your worthy anceſters, be you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined in a coniunction of vnſeparable aid, that the body of the tree may be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſo happy an iſſue, and in the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt blaſt of conſpiracie keepe you ſtill vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoueable.</p>
               <p>Be you like faithfull <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in your wayes, when traitors like proud <hi>Hamon</hi> ſhall periſh in their own complots.</p>
               <p>For if you pleaſe to peruſe our hiſtories, both Eccleſiaſtical &amp; profane, ye ſhall find that neuer traitor to his Prince &amp; country but had his reward threefold returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wicked boſome. And though it pleaſe God ſometime to ſuffer them, the cauſe beſt knowne to his ſacred pleaſure, to bring to paſſe their hateful purpoſes, yet as a woe pronounced to them by whom ſuch euils come, their miſchiefe hath not paſt without greater miſchiefes reguerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>There is none of your honorable ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie but knowes, that treaſon is the deuider
<pb facs="tcp:11833:8"/>
and ſeparater of all good good things, and a fatall diſioyner of perfection, bringing with it ruine and the mercileſſe ſubſtitutes of war: where on the contrary, obedience is the ſinewes of the State, and glueth the hearts of Nobilitie together, like one indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>And as the ſeuen leane kine in Pharaoes dreame, deuoured the ſeuen fat (yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not the fatter:) ſo ſtands it with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, like a cormorant it deuoures all, yet is it ſelfe the better by nothing. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter patterne of miſery can there be, then a kingdome deuided in it ſelfe? It is like the dangerous eclips of the ſunne: nay like the vnnatural ſeparation of heauen, that brings all danger and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>No plague of Aegypt comparable to that miſery: for ciuill diſſention is the gate to let in ruine and forraine inuaſion.</p>
               <p>It is like a wedge of Iron, that entring into an oake, diſſeuers both ſides in ſeueral peeces, &amp; makes them both fit for the fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11833:9"/>
The flouriſhing ſtate of Rome was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by that monſter, and all tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſwallowed at a bit by that hideous Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiathan. It is like the blind Mole, that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtill to be miſchieuouſly labouring, toſſeth vp her owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Let then (right Honorable) that accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſacrifice of your hearts be offered to our gracious Soueraigne, which farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the externall office of fained affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who with an eye of vigilance will (no doubt) regard your vertues; and like the chearefull comfort of the Sunne, with his bleſſed countenance, make your young bloſſomes come to pleaſant fruite, and bring that fruite by comfortable warmth to full maturitie.</p>
               <p>God ſo direct your hearts to worke in you vnfained loyaltie to his royal Maieſty, and deadly hatred to ſelfe-deuouring trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:9"/>
               <head>To the true and faithfull priuate ſubiect.</head>
               <p>ANd now beloued countrey-men, to you in generall, that carry with you the ful currant of affection, the ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtreame of deep gliding loue, not to be reuerted or turned backe by the vehement oppoſition of any reſiſting wind.</p>
               <p>To you, as to the open marke whereto my hart leuels her pretended ayme, being the vpſhot of mine exhortation, I ſend this louing and friendly counſell, like to a ſtrong citie fenced about with impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble walles, ſo ought you to be in time of domeſtical Rebellion, or forrain inuaſion: for you are the maine battel, the truſt and ſtrength of your country, and to you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs a chiefe truſt in this required preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Euen as his Highneſſe may wel be compared to the apple of our eie, of which naturally by reaſon it is tender vnto vs,
<pb facs="tcp:11833:10"/>
We haue a diligent care. So ought you to ioyne your whole body of defence, both armes, legges, feet and heart, to protect his royall perſon, without ſecret grudging, priuate muttering, or vnnaturall contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie. You ought to be like ſtedfaſt rockes in the ſea, ready to front euery ſtorme, and to withſtand, without remouing, the moſt bitter blaſts that either winter or foule weather affoords.</p>
               <p>I know my moſt louing countreymen, that you well perceiue the princely care of his Maieſtie towards you his louing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and the honorable diſpoſition and noble induſtry of his vigilant Councel. Of which honourable ſocietie, although now vntimely deceaſſed, I cannot but call to mind that right honorable and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to be remembred, the late <hi>L. Burgley,</hi> and <hi>Lord high Treaſurer of England:</hi> whoſe fame may not be ſealed vp with the leade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand of obliuion, who whileſt he liued ſhewed himſelfe one of the moſt faithfull,
<pb facs="tcp:11833:10"/>
carefull, and wiſe Councellers that euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in any kingdome of Chriſtendome. He was the Beacon that diſcouered forrain malice and home-bred miſchiefe, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-failing watchtower of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the heart of Iuſtice, bearing vp the ballance of weightie cauſes with an euen hand, and cutting downe with the ſharpe ſword of preuention the children of rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion at home, and the enuious intention of the enemie abroad.</p>
               <p>For cauſes in common triall, I call hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to witneſſe, I ſpeake but what I know, as he was iudiciall, wary and circumſpect, ſo was he vpright, diſcreete, and pittifull, not leaning to any ſide either for fauour or gift, but with an impartiall eye iudging all things according to the equitie of the cauſe. Thankes be to God, the principall branches of that tree do now moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſpread their vertue in this his Maieſties garden of happie gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11833:11"/>
In which ranke of true Nobilitie, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent watchmen, and worthy Councellers, I may not omit that right honorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned Lord the Earle of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> whoſe true loyaltie to his Maieſtie, neuer ſpotted with the leaſt miſtruſt, may keepe euen wing with the reſt of that Honorable ſociety: whoſe true ſhew of a vertuous and noble mind, is dayly made apparant by his exceeding bounty towards the poore and needy. The fruite whereof is eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>And that reuerent and carefull Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Sir Iohn Popham</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England, being another of the body of the Councell, whoſe honorable forwardneſſe, with great diſcretion hath bin now lately approued in his Maieſties ſerious affaires, as alſo in calming the Realme with quiet, that hath bin hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tempeſtuouſly troubled with bloudy murtherers and felonious robbers: but now (God be thanked) by his diligent
<pb facs="tcp:11833:11"/>
and wiſe gouernement, well reformed; whoſe exceeding loue to his Prince and countrey, hath bin often made apparant by his laborious endeuours.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I beſeech God in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercie, ſtirre vp in you deare affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting loue to his Maieſtie, who for the comfort of his choſen, and maintenance of his truth, hath defended his Highneſſe as well in Scotland as now in England, from many dangerous aſſaults, and here now ſetled him the faithfull Preſident of his true Church, wherin long may his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie continue many happie and peaceful daies, to the great glory of God, and to the exceeding comfort of all vs his faithfull and louing ſubiects. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="thanksgiving">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:12"/>
            <head>A Thankſgiuing to God for the happie deliuerance of the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty, the Queen, Prince, Nobilitie, and Commons, from the moſt horrible contriued treaſon, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt them in the high Court of Parliament, tending to the vtter deſolation and ruine of all his Maieſties kingdomes; but preuented by the almightie proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the onely prudent fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of the Kings moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REioyce O Brittaine, ſing and clap thy hands,</l>
               <l>For God himſelfe doth for thee ſafely fight:</l>
               <l>No foe ſo great, but that thy force withſtands,</l>
               <l>It is ſo ſtrengthened by the heauenly might.</l>
               <l>The Popes great malice, and the Papiſts pride,</l>
               <l>Before thy face do fall on euery ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:12"/>
               <l>Now ſhalt thou heare of nothing but confuſion</l>
               <l>Vpon the head of all thy harmefull foes:</l>
               <l>Now ſhall the traitors find the full concluſion,</l>
               <l>That in the end of all rebellion growes:</l>
               <l>And they ſhall fret to ſee their pride puld downe,</l>
               <l>Whilſt God preſerues thy ſoueraigne &amp; his crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſhall the Pope with all his practiſe faile,</l>
               <l>The hope of traitors all be ouerthrowne:</l>
               <l>Nor Pope nor traitor now ſhall none preuaile,</l>
               <l>To do thee hurt that but defendſt thine owne.</l>
               <l>Now ſerue thy God, and giue him thankes for all,</l>
               <l>And keepe thy ſaith, and thou ſhalt neuer fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be true (I ſay) and faithfull to thy God,</l>
               <l>And euer loyall to thy ſoueraigne King,</l>
               <l>For whoſe loue ſake we haue eſcapt this rod,</l>
               <l>Which otherwiſe had ſcourg'd vs for our ſin:</l>
               <l>He will not ſuffer any to deſtroy thee,</l>
               <l>But ouerthrow their forces that annoy thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:13"/>
               <l>In Scotland late how did he in that land</l>
               <l>Preſerue the King from traitrous Gowries treaſon:</l>
               <l>And by the helpe of worthy Ramſeys hand</l>
               <l>Did ſlay the traitor, as it was but reaſon:</l>
               <l>Where noble Ramſey by deſerued fame,</l>
               <l>Eterniz'd hath the honour of his name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now let all hearts of happie Brittaine pray</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto our God of glorious mercies power,</l>
               <l>That he will ſtill be our almightie ſtay,</l>
               <l>Our rocke, our castle, and our heauenly tower:</l>
               <l>That in his mercie we may feareleſſe liue,</l>
               <l>And to his gracious loue all glorie giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let vs ſtill pray that he will ſtill preſerue</l>
               <l>Our gracious King in his eternall grace,</l>
               <l>And giue vs grace him truly for to ſerue,</l>
               <l>And all vnfaithfull traitors to deface:</l>
               <l>To ſpend our liues but in our countries cauſe,</l>
               <l>And be obedient to his bleſſed lawes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:13"/>
               <l>Rebellion is a ſinne of witchcraft named,</l>
               <l>And witches are but diuels in their natures:</l>
               <l>O helliſh fiends to the diuell framed,</l>
               <l>Which ſo deceiue but the accurſed creatures.</l>
               <l>O curſed Sin, that euer man ſhould know thee!</l>
               <l>God bleſſe King Iames and al his ſubiects fro thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince that truth doth try out euery thought,</l>
               <l>Whereon the depth of euery ſence is ſounded,</l>
               <l>Againſt that truth who hath the treaſon wrought,</l>
               <l>That on vngracious reaſon hath bene grounded.</l>
               <l>What euer fortune for a time do fall,</l>
               <l>Confuſions ſhame will be the end of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God grant it ſo, and with his gracious hand</l>
               <l>Long bleſſe the daies of our dread ſoueraigne King,</l>
               <l>And make him Emperour of this bleſſed land,</l>
               <l>Till no more land within the world be ſeene:</l>
               <l>And make his conqueſts euermore victorious,</l>
               <l>And all his kingdomes in thy mercie glorious.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:14"/>
               <l>Bleſſe valiant Ramſey with that mount of ioy,</l>
               <l>That noble truth in trueſt nobleneſſe,</l>
               <l>May ſtand ſo ſtrong, as nothing may deſtroy:</l>
               <l>But in the height of honours happineſſe</l>
               <l>May by the vertue of beſt valure proued,</l>
               <l>Of God and man be bleſſed and beloued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bleſſe all his Councell, and his faithfull friends,</l>
               <l>Court, cities, countries, all in ſuch a peace,</l>
               <l>As all the world that ſees proud traitors ends,</l>
               <l>May cauſe the roote of all rebellion ceaſe:</l>
               <l>Such peace and plentie, loue and concord ſend,</l>
               <l>That we may ſing thy glorie without end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pray now with me, and prayer neuer ceaſe</l>
               <l>Vnto the God of all eternall glorie,</l>
               <l>His life, his health, his comfort to increaſe,</l>
               <l>To Brittaines bliſſe and neuer ending ſtorie,</l>
               <l>That he may breathe an euerlaſting breath,</l>
               <l>And thoſe may pine in hell that ſeeke his death.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="thanksgiving">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:14"/>
            <head>A Thankſgiuing to God for all our temporall bleſſings.</head>
            <head type="sub">O praiſe the Lord for euer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Heauenly ſpirit of eſpeciall power,</l>
               <l>That in thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the praiſe of praiſes holdeſt,</l>
               <l>And from the top of truths triumphant tower,</l>
               <l>The hidden ſence of faireſt thoughts vnfoldeſt:</l>
               <l>Inſpire this heart and humble ſoule of mine,</l>
               <l>With ſome ſweet ſparkle of thy powr diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Teach me to thinke but on that onely thought,</l>
               <l>Wherin doth liue the grace of vertues glorie,</l>
               <l>And learn no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what thy truth hath taught</l>
               <l>To thoſe best wits that write thy worthy ſtorie,</l>
               <l>Wherein is ſeene in heauen and earths preſeruing,</l>
               <l>The higheſt point of praiſes due deſeruing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:15"/>
               <l>Let not compare come neare vnto none ſuch,</l>
               <l>Heauen be my thought, and let the world go by,</l>
               <l>And ſay withall, that ſay I neuer ſo much,</l>
               <l>All are but trifles to thy treaſury:</l>
               <l>For all no more then what thy mercie giueth,</l>
               <l>Who can behold wherein thy glorie liueth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, I can ſee the ſhining of the Sunne,</l>
               <l>But cannot ſound the eſſence of the light:</l>
               <l>Then of thy face, in whom that faire begun,</l>
               <l>How can my ſoule preſume to haue a ſight?</l>
               <l>No my deare God, thy glorie hath a being,</l>
               <l>Where eye, nor heart, nor ſoule may haue a ſeeing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore Lord ſince ſuch thy glorie is,</l>
               <l>As cannot be but of thy ſelfe conceiued:</l>
               <l>And heauen nor earth containes that ſpark of bliſſe</l>
               <l>But from thy hand of mercie is receiued,</l>
               <l>What ſpirit can her ſweeteſt paſſion raiſe,</l>
               <l>Neare to the due of thy deſerued praiſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:15"/>
               <l>Yet ſince all glorie doth belong to thee,</l>
               <l>Thy name in all things muſt be magnified:</l>
               <l>And by thy mercie thou haſt made me ſee</l>
               <l>How in my ſoule thou maiſt be glorified:</l>
               <l>In that ſweete mercie make my ſoule to know</l>
               <l>How beſt I may thy bleſſed glorie ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O gracious God, what creature can there be,</l>
               <l>That moues, or breathes, or growes, but ſhewes thy glory?</l>
               <l>What art or ſcience but doth ſpeak of thee,</l>
               <l>And writes the wonder of thy wiſedomes ſtory?</l>
               <l>What ſound or ſence can reaſons ſoule refine,</l>
               <l>But ſpeakes in glorie of thy grace diuine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sunne in brightneſſe glorifies the light</l>
               <l>That in the beames but of thy beautie liueth,</l>
               <l>The Moone and ſtarres amid the darkeſt night</l>
               <l>Shew what a light thy louing mercie giueth:</l>
               <l>So Sun and Moone, and all thoſe ſhining creatures</l>
               <l>Do ſhew thy glorie in their light ſome natures.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:16"/>
               <l>Is not the day a figure of perfection,</l>
               <l>Wherein the creatures were created firſt,</l>
               <l>And night of ſinne, that with a foule infection</l>
               <l>Shewes how the ſoule is for her ſinnes accurſt?</l>
               <l>But night once paſt, the glorious day appearing</l>
               <l>Shewes ſinnes forgiuen, the ioy of mercies chearing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So Sun, and Moon, and ſtarres, and day, and night,</l>
               <l>Speakes of thy glorie in their cauſe of being:</l>
               <l>And how they ſerue but in obedience right</l>
               <l>Vnto thy grace, but of thy will agreeing,</l>
               <l>While wiſedome ſhewes in ſtate of reaſons ſtorie,</l>
               <l>They giue vs light that we may giue thee glorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The azure skie more cleare then Chriſtalline,</l>
               <l>Wherein the Sune doth cast his beames abroad:</l>
               <l>How doth it figure that faire hand of thine,</l>
               <l>Wherein thy mercie makes her moſt abode,</l>
               <l>Whilſt to the humble ſoules beleeuing eye,</l>
               <l>Thy glorie ſhines farre brighter then the skie?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:16"/>
               <l>The clouds that ſhed thoſe drops of bleſſed deawes,</l>
               <l>That water the drie places of the earth:</l>
               <l>What drop ſo ſmall, but it thy glorie ſhewes,</l>
               <l>To bring a plentie where was earſt a dearth?</l>
               <l>How do they figure faithfull ſorowes teares,</l>
               <l>When ſin-burnt ſoules the fruite of mercie beares?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ayre that giues each liuing creature breath,</l>
               <l>Speakes of thy glorie in that breathing power:</l>
               <l>And when it leaues the creature vnto death,</l>
               <l>It ſhewes thy glorie in that parting houre,</l>
               <l>To leaue the fleſh, ſo in corruption wounded,</l>
               <l>Till grace renew that was in ſinne confounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The earth that yeelds ſuch choice of fruits &amp; flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</l>
               <l>How doth it ſhew that glorious power of thine,</l>
               <l>When all vnſeene do hidden lye thoſe powers,</l>
               <l>That art or nature neuer can define?</l>
               <l>How ſweets, &amp; formes, and colours ſo ſhould grow,</l>
               <l>But that thy glorius will would haue it ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:17"/>
               <l>And as the ſpring brings forth the budding greene,</l>
               <l>With beauties dies for to adorne the field:</l>
               <l>So in the winter few or none are ſeene,</l>
               <l>That can the eye contentiue pleaſure yeeld.</l>
               <l>So that the earth which neuer ſilence breaketh,</l>
               <l>In her dumbe ſpeech yet of thy glorie ſpeaketh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſea, wherein thoſe world of fiſhes liue,</l>
               <l>That flote and tumble in the toſſing waues:</l>
               <l>What notice do they of thy glorie giue,</l>
               <l>That from the Whale the little Herring ſaues?</l>
               <l>And makes the Dolphin wound the Whale ſo ſore,</l>
               <l>As driues him from the ſea to die on ſhore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What beaſt ſo great, or creeping worme ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>What bird ſo high, or of ſo low a flight,</l>
               <l>But that thy name is glorifide in all?</l>
               <l>Who hauing made them by thy heauenly might,</l>
               <l>Preſeru'ſt them ſo, that all the world may ſee,</l>
               <l>They haue their being onely but in thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:17"/>
               <l>The beaſt his haire, the feather of the bird,</l>
               <l>The fiſh his ſcale, and euery tree his barke:</l>
               <l>Theſe for defence doth nature all afford,</l>
               <l>As of thy glorie euery one a marke,</l>
               <l>Wherein thy hand of mercie is beheld,</l>
               <l>That doth ſuch comfort to each creature yeeld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is not the fire a figure of thy wrath,</l>
               <l>That ſoone conſumes the proud aſſault of ſinne?</l>
               <l>The aire the patience that thy mercie hath,</l>
               <l>When true contrition doth remiſſion winne?</l>
               <l>The water teares that thou for ſinne hast ſhed,</l>
               <l>The earth thy death for to redeeme the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since then aboue and in the elements,</l>
               <l>Sun, Moone, ſtars, skie, fire, water, earth and aire,</l>
               <l>And what may be beneath the firmament,</l>
               <l>Beaſts, birds, fiſh, worme, ſcale, fether, hide or haire,</l>
               <l>Nor tree, nor flower, nor herb, nor graſſe doth grow</l>
               <l>But ſome way doth thy glorious mercie ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:18"/>
               <l>Shall wretched man, whom God did onely make</l>
               <l>To his owne image in his mercies loue,</l>
               <l>So farre himſelfe and all his good forſake,</l>
               <l>As to forget ſo ſweete a Turtle-doue</l>
               <l>As his deare God, that ſo of nothing wrought him,</l>
               <l>And his deare Son that hath ſo dearly bought him?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shall man I ſay, that onely ſpeciall creature,</l>
               <l>Whom God hath made to ſerue his Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>In lacke of grace reueale ſo vile a nature,</l>
               <l>As not to ſeeke his name to glorifie?</l>
               <l>No, heauens forbid, though ſinne be neuer ſuch</l>
               <l>In man ſhould liue ingratitude ſo much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, he whom God hath made to monarke ſo</l>
               <l>Aboue all creatures that do grow or breathe:</l>
               <l>And by his wiſedome makes his will to know</l>
               <l>The good aboue, and euill from beneath:</l>
               <l>And how he helpes the ſpirit in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>His glorious goodneſſe cannot but confeſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:18"/>
               <l>And when he ſees with thoſe in-ſeeing eyes,</l>
               <l>That in the ſoule do giue the ſpirit light,</l>
               <l>In what the height of heauenly glorie lies,</l>
               <l>To whom all glorie doth belong of right:</l>
               <l>His heart will write in his worths worthy ſtorie,</l>
               <l>To him alone be giuen all onely glorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O he that ſits aboue the ſtarrie skie,</l>
               <l>In holy ſeate of heauenly reſidence,</l>
               <l>And at the twinkling of his glorious eye,</l>
               <l>Commaunds the world to his obedience:</l>
               <l>Leaue that foule ſoule in ſorrow euer friendleſſe,</l>
               <l>That doth not ſound thy name in glorie endleſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All grace, all goodnes, wiſedome, power and peace,</l>
               <l>All truth, true life, all bountie, mercie, loue,</l>
               <l>Theſe altogether ſing and neuer ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Vnto the glorie of this God aboue:</l>
               <l>And can it be that man who ſees all this,</l>
               <l>Will not giue glorie to this God of his?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:19"/>
               <l>No, heauens forbid that hell ſhould haue the power</l>
               <l>To ſpit her poiſon vpon man ſo much,</l>
               <l>To make him liue to that vnhappie houre,</l>
               <l>Wherein to ſhew his wicked nature ſuch,</l>
               <l>As to forget Gods gracious goodneſſe ſo,</l>
               <l>As not ſome way his glorious mercie ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let our hearts amongst that world of ſoules,</l>
               <l>That feele his bleſſings euery day and houre,</l>
               <l>While truth records in her eternall roules,</l>
               <l>The gracious goodneſſe of his glorious power,</l>
               <l>Sing in our ſoules, and neuer ceaſe to ſing,</l>
               <l>All glorie to our God, and honour to our King.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:11833:19"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the Kings most excellent Maiestie, and our gracious Ladie Queene Anne.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Glorious God and onely King of Kings,</l>
               <l>Whoſe holy eye both heauen and earth behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth:</l>
               <l>And from whoſe mercy all and onely ſprings,</l>
               <l>The fairest life that faithfull loue vnfoldeth:</l>
               <l>Mine humble ſpirit I beſeech thee raiſe,</l>
               <l>To giue thy glorie all eternall praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O gracious God, among the many graces,</l>
               <l>Wherewith thy mercy hath this kingdome bleſt,</l>
               <l>In whom the height of all our happie caſes,</l>
               <l>Vnder thine onely holy hand doth reſt:</l>
               <l>For our Liege (Lord) and mightie Brittains King,</l>
               <l>Let our hearts humble thankefulneſſe be ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:20"/>
               <l>Bleſſe him (ô Lord) with Neſtors happie dayes,</l>
               <l>Health, wealth and peace, and euerlaſting pleaſure:</l>
               <l>Let vertues loue reſound his worthy praiſe,</l>
               <l>And thy true wiſedome be his ſpirits treaſure,</l>
               <l>His greateſt hopes vpon thy graces grounded,</l>
               <l>His ſtate preſerued, and his foes confounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bleſſe alſo (Lord) our gracious Soueraignes Queen</l>
               <l>With all the bleſſings of thy holy grace,</l>
               <l>And let it neuer in this land be ſeene,</l>
               <l>But in thy mercie they may both haue place:</l>
               <l>Nor ſweete Prince Henries fame die in obliuions pen:</l>
               <l>To all of theſe true Brittans ſay Amen.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11833:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
